<<<<<<< Updated upstream
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-03T14:42:57-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Carson Bailey</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Battle Royale Narrative Formula!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-battle-royale-narrative-formula.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Battle Royale Narrative Formula!" /><published>2022-10-31T22:12:26-04:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T22:12:26-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-battle-royale-narrative-formula</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-battle-royale-narrative-formula.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-a-battle-royale">What is a battle royale?</h2>

<p>A battle that involves many combatants, but ends with only one contestant left standing.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-battle-royale-narrative-formula">What is the battle royale narrative formula?</h2>

<p>The battle royale narrative formula often partakes of elements from science-fiction and horror genres to build a fictional narrative where a specific group of people are forced into a contest where they have to fight until only one person is left alive. This contest is sponsored by the powerful and exploits the powerless, who are usually the contestants. The survivor of the competition is often given some form of reward from the power system that put the battle into place. These narratives examine the oppression of various types of groups (most commonly race, class, age, and gender) and how people respond when put into a kill or be killed situation. More often than not, these battle royale narrative formulas are centered around adolescents or marketed for adolescents.</p>

<p>The battle royale narrative formula pervades current culture in various forms of media, including reality television.
This includes shows like <em>Survivor</em> and <em>American Idol</em>. Battle royale narrative formulas can also be seen in literature through books like Suzanne Collins’ <em>The Hunger Games</em> and Amanda Foody’s <em>All of Us Villians</em>. These formulas are also seen in video games like <em>Fortnite</em> and television shows like Netflix’s <em>Squid Games</em>.</p>

<h2 id="the-battle-royale-narrative-formula-and-adolescents">The battle royale narrative formula and adolescents.</h2>

<p>When looking at popular culture and the battle royale narrative formulas success, we can understand its roots with adolescents, particularly when thinking in terms of video games, YA novels, and reality television shows. In order to understand this we have to ask the right questions. Some of these questions include understanding why developing as members of society and as individuals, so enraptured by a brutal, gory, and emotionally and physically violent narrative formula?</p>

<p>While the idea of teenagers consuming vast quantities of violence is unsettling, it is not unsurprising, for these narratives often promote a sense of identity or establishing an individual identity. The recent appearance of this formula is actually a result of history, the notion of an adolescent or someone transitioning into a new identity with increased maturity being non-existent.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is a battle royale?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The History of the Battle Royale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-history-of-the-battle-royale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The History of the Battle Royale" /><published>2022-10-31T22:12:26-04:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T22:12:26-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-history-of-the-battle-royale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/2022/10/31/the-history-of-the-battle-royale.html"><![CDATA[<p>The historical origins of the battle royale go as far back as over 300 years old, with a brief stint in 18th century England boxing, before really starting somewhere unexpected: slavery. Battle royals became popular in American slave culture. The slave population (primarily of African descent) referred to these battle royals as a “free-for-all” where any number of men would compete in a boxing ring, picking “whichever opponent he desired’’ (Slave Narratives) until only one man was left standing. While these battle royals were held and organized by slaves on days of celebration, the battle royal would be heavily attended by white people. The battle royals of African people did not die with the American Civil War and the abolition of slaves, but instead became entertainment for the white population, with the participants competing for a monetary prize.</p>

<p>Many newspapers have ads for these battle royals, promoting that they had “reserved plenty of seats for white fans’’ (Sarasota Herald- Tribune, Jan 20 1933).  The Brownsville Herald advertised a boxing match that would be opened with a “negro battle to set the fans in a cheery mood.” Battle royals provided white people with the oppportunity to mock and demean the black population even after the abolishment slavery. To establish a sense of unrest within the slave community was “among the most effective in the hands of the slaveholder in keeping down the spirit of insurrection” (Frederick Douglass). The battle royal as a power struggle in Southern American culture in the early 1900’s is comparable to the battle royale subgenre that also lays out these fights as the product of a hierarchical power system focused on oppressing and weakening a targeted population. This is important in understanding the role the battle royale has in a historical context and has some influence over the battle royale narrative formula itself, as demonstrated in the precursor texts of the battle royale narrative formula texts.</p>

<p>Almost all college and high school students who take a literature course will stumble (often unknowingly) across the precursor to the battle royale narrative formula in the form of two classic works: William Golding’s Lord of the Flies and Ralph Ellison’s short story (and opening chapter of Invisible Man) “Battle Royal.” Each of these texts are frequently taught and used to examine identity and human nature and can be connected to historical movements. By making these texts staples for adolescent education, the school system is exposing the young and impressionable mind to varying forms and expressions of identity within a hierarchical power.</p>

<p>Before the abolishment of the institution of slavery the battle royal was “among the most effective in the hands of the slaveholder in keeping down the spirit of insurrection” (Douglass) and this power dynamic had not changed in 1947 when this chapter was published ing a magazine befor being published in his 1952 novel.</p>

<p>Participating in the battle royal is coercion of commodification because it is necessary for these boys to make money. The want for money is a purposeful consequence of the hierarchy, which purposefully leaves the black population beneath the poverty line, forcing them to commodify themselves. They are selling themselves as a result of “severe inequality [and] dire economic necessity” (Leong 2199) needing the money to have access to the bare minimum for survival, such as food, shelter, and clothing. Commodifying humans, like enslaved individuals in a battle royal, endangers personhood, violating the fundamental concepts of being human: freedom, identity, and the role in one’s environment (Leong 2200). This endangerment of personhood is a driving force in the idea of battle royals because it not only emphasizes the varying values of human life, but the social structures that enforce these extreme biases.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The historical origins of the battle royale go as far back as over 300 years old, with a brief stint in 18th century England boxing, before really starting somewhere unexpected: slavery. Battle royals became popular in American slave culture. The slave population (primarily of African descent) referred to these battle royals as a “free-for-all” where any number of men would compete in a boxing ring, picking “whichever opponent he desired’’ (Slave Narratives) until only one man was left standing. While these battle royals were held and organized by slaves on days of celebration, the battle royal would be heavily attended by white people. The battle royals of African people did not die with the American Civil War and the abolition of slaves, but instead became entertainment for the white population, with the participants competing for a monetary prize.]]></summary></entry></feed>
=======
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-31T23:23:52-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/carsonbailey/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Carson Bailey</title><subtitle></subtitle></feed>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
